A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Ford Foundation History Project FA251
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Ford Foundation History Project
1979-1996
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
Garrison, Lloyd
FA251
0.8 Cubic Feet 2 letter document containers
Biographical / Historical
Lloyd Garrison was Director of the Office of Communications at the Ford Foundation from 1991 to 1995. In May 1995, he left the Office of Communications to research, write, and edit an authorized history, in book or video form, of the Ford Foundation from 1980-1995. The project had a deadline of May 1996 most likely to coincide with the retirement of Ford Foundation president Franklin Thomas. Garrison left the Foundation after the project ended in 1996. It appears the project never moved beyond a collection of drafts.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into one series: Lloyd Garrison's Files on the Ford Foundation History Project
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was transferred to RAC in 2019 by the Ford Foundation and ingested by RAC as Accession 2019:146.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Related Materials
The Ford Foundation: A History Draft, Lloyd Garrison, Director, Foundation History Project, undated in Ford Foundation records, Publications (Non-Grant Related), Accession 2017:050, 1949-2016
Scope and Contents
The collection is comprised of material related to the Ford Foundation History Project led by Lloyd Garrison, former Director of the Ford Foundation's Office of Communications. The collection contains chapter outlines, chapter drafts, lists of other corporate/institutional history projects, research materials, project updates, meeting notes, and memos primarily from 1995-1996.
Ford Foundation; Ford Foundation -- History
- Lloyd Garrison's Files on the Ford Foundation History Project
  - Memos Regarding the Ford Foundation and South Africa, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes: Ford Foundation History Project - "South Africa: Making a Difference" outline, chapter summary, and South Africa History Project Timeline (Historical timeline alongside Ford Foundation programmatic timeline)
  - Urban Local Governance - Papers, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    The Ford Foundation and the Urban Poor in the 1950s by Alice O'Connor
    Anti-Delinquency, Great Cities, Gray Areas
  - Community Development - Papers, 1981-1996 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
    Chapter Outline
    Thomas Quinn's Draft Report of the Ford Foundation -- CDCs
    Community Development Partnerships
    Support for Emerging Community Development Corporations, Ford Foundation, March 1983
    Preliminary Recommendations on the Foundation's Future Directions, Ford Foundation, March 1981, Board of Trustees Meeting
    Articles: Urban Community Development
    Articles: Rural Community Development
    Grants Listing of Urban and Rural Community Development
    Ford Foundation Supported Community Development Corporations and Ford Foundation Work in Teenage Pregnancy
  - The Ford Foundation Library: Selected Bibliography on the Ford Foundation 1949-1950, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Environment and Development in Haiti, Michel-Rolph Trouillot, Johns Hopkins, 1993 August (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence - General, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Correspondence regarding W. McNeil Lowry's personal papers at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign and New York, N.Y.: A Television Series of Problem-Solving Town Meetings, Batten/Silverstein
  - Bi-Weekly Activity Reports, 1995 June-1996 June (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Women and Family - Ford Foundation History Project, 1996 February (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Program Directors' Memos on History Project, 1995 June-July (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Democracy and Civil Society (Office Memos) - Ford Foundation History Project, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - International Human Rights Program, Ford Foundation, 1996 July (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Beijing Conference, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    The Ford Foundation and Beijing
    United Nations IV World Conference on Women
    NGO Forum on Women
    The Women's Program Forum and Beijing
    Foundation Programming Related to Beijing
  - Economic Policy Analysis by Louis Winnick, 1979 March 10 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Memorandum for the Trustees from McGeorge Bundy
    Discussion Paper - "The Facts Have Changed:" A New Look at Economic Policy Analysis
  - History Project Meetings, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 15-18)
  - History Project (Institutional Histories), 1995 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Women's Studies: A Retrospective, A Report to the Ford Foundation by Beverly Guy-Sheftall with Susan Heath, 1995 June (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - The Ford Foundation: A History, Tom Quinn, circa 1991 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Background Materials, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 22)